Ivy City Oral History Project OHP.027
People's Archive, MLK Library
Ivy City Oral History Project Collection
2005-2007
People's Archive, MLK Library
Drake, Ingrid
Ivy City Achievers
OHP.027
0.25 Linear feet
1 Boxes
Arrangement
This collection is housed in one box, 0.25 linear feet, and contains two series. The first series is organized alphabetically by last name of interviewee on the CD (some CDs contain multiple interviews, and group interviews), and contains 23 folders. The second series contains color 4"x6" photographs of some of the interviewees.
Arrangement
This collection is housed in one box and contains two series. The first series is organized alphabetically by last name of interviewee on the CD (some CDs contain multiple interviews, and group interviews), and contains 23 folders. The second series contains color 4"x6" photographs of some of the interviewees. Series 1: Oral Histories Series 2: Photographs
Biographical / Historical
Ingrid Drake, CGAP (Certified Government Auditing Professional), is a program analyst with the Office of District of Columbia Auditor (OD.C.A). Previously, she was an investigator for the Washington-based nonprofit Project On Government Oversight (POGO); and was a writer, Pacifica Radio correspondent, and community educator living in Washington, D.C. In 2007 at the time of gift, she was a local D.C. journalist, writing for several outlets: D.C. North, East of the River, Hill Rag, D.C. Radio Co-op, www.D.C.Indymedia.org, WPFW 89.3 FM - Pacifica Radio, and Free Speech Radio News. Her contact information is: IngridNatasha@yahoo.com.
Related Materials
The information in the interviews was used in a book, African Americans and Gentrification in Washington, DC: Race, Class and Social Justice in the Nation's Capital, by Sabhiya Prince (New York: Routledge, 2014).
Related Materials
The information in the interviews was used in a book, "African Americans and Gentrification in Washington, D.C.: Race, Class and Social Justice in the Nation's Capital," by Sabhiya Prince (New York: Routledge, 2014).
Scope and Contents
From 2005 and 2007, Ingrid Drake coordinated the Ivy City Oral History Project, in collaboration with the youth of Ivy City Achievers. She interviewed and supervised interviews with residents of the Ivy City neighborhood of Washington, D.C. The project was part of a larger initiative of Empower D.C., a grassroots nonprofit in D.C., called the Ivy City Neighborhood and Oral History Project, which began in 2004. The larger initiative arose from a plan to preserve Alexander Crummell School in the Ivy City neighborhood. Empower D.C. received funding for their efforts to document Ivy City's history from the Humanities Council of Washington, D.C. The resulting interviews were published in Ivy City Neighborhood and Oral History Project Booklet, an Empower D.C. project. Additionally, Ingrid Drake produced a radio show for WPFW 89.3 FM of the final interviews. The interviewees discuss a history of black migration to Ivy City from the South, work histories, Ivy City memories, neighborhood churches, Sparrow's Beach (a private beach in Annapolis, Maryland for black vacationers during the Jim Crow Era of racial segregation, Alexander Crummell Elementary School, the 1968 D.C. uprising, neighborhood changes over time, drug use in the 1970s, Ivy City activism, gentrification, housing advocacy, Empower D.C., and the future of Ivy City. The Ivy City Oral History Project collection is comprised of 23 audio CDs (21 CDs of interviews of 24 people, plus one CD of transcripts in the form of 16 Word [97-2003 version] documents of 19 interviews, and one CD of the final radio show), and 11 color 4"x6" photographs of 13 of the 24 interviewees. There are no transcripts for some interviewees. The radio show contains snippets of interviews interwoven with popular commercially-recorded music. Interviewed are 24 people: Aaron Aylor, Charles H. Brown, Alfred Coates, Theodore Coates, Clifford Coulson, Lula "Jackie" Council, Erica Crews, Okia Ferguson, Remetter Freeman, Dorothy "Nicey" Gary, Eleanor Grant, Sarah Parker Hunter, Marjorie Jones, Aujeneah Milner, Joel McPherson, Mohammed Mobaidin, Parisa Norouzi, Audrey Ray, Margaret Rice, Elaine Smith, Kenneth Tapscott, Romaine Thomas, Charlotte Tyner and Daisy Wroten.
Oral History; Photographs; Ivy City (Washington, D.C.); Neighborhoods; African Americans; Families; Black persons
- Series 1: Oral Histories
  - Ivy City Oral History Project, 2005-6, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Final radio show plus jewel case back text. CD-R, 700 MB, 80 min. Fuji. In plastic CD jewel case. Notes on cover include: A project of: Empower DC, the DC Radio Co-op, Crummell Alumni, DC Commission on Arts and the Humanities, and DC Humanities Council. Copyright 2006, My Company, Inc. All rights reserved. Thanks to all the people who agreed to be interviewed: Aaron Aylor, Charles Brown, Alfred and Theodore Coates, Colbert Coulson, Jackie Council, Erica Crews, Dorothy "Nicey" Gary, Eleanor Grant, Remetter Freeman, Okia Ferguson, Sarah Hunter, Marjorie Jones, Joel McPherson, Augeneah Milner, Parisa Norouzi, Audrey Ray, Margaret Rice, Elaine Smith, Kenneth Tapscott, Romaine Thomas, Charlotte Tyner, and Daisy Wroten. Without your help this would not be possible: Remetter Freeman, Bethesda Baptishs Church, Marcus Crews, Tony Crews, Sean Crews, Percy Williams, Antwan Williams, Ivan Blake, Aujeneah Milner, Greg Tyson, Ryme Katkhouda, Calenthia Dowdy, Catherine Benedict, Zainabu Dance, Dave Bosserman, Gail Taylor, Cathy Meals, Lauren Barthel, Ellen Chenoweth, Morgan Drake, Roshin Mathew, Schuyler Borton, Emily Rudicell, Lauren Boegen, WPFW Radio 89.3 FM, DC Indymedia - www.dc.indymedia.org. Produced by Ingrid Drake. ingridnatasha@yahoo.com
  - Aaron Aylor - 44:35 - Empower DC's Ivy City Oral History Project 7/15/06, 2006-07-15 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Entire CD is Aaron Aylor interview. CD-R, 700 MB, 80 min. Memorex. In purple plastic sleeve.
  - Charles Brown Ivy City Oral History Project 8/2/06, 2006-08-02 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Entire CD is Charles Brown interview. CD-R Audio, 80 min. Sony. In purple plastic sleeve.
  - Alfred and Theodore Coates - 60:23 - Empower DC's Ivy City Oral History Project 6/20/05, 2005-06-20 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Entire CD is Alfred and Theodore Coates interviews. CD-R, 700 MB, 80 min. Memorex. One disc in blue plastic sleeve.
  - Clifford Coulson - 24:23 - Empower DC's Ivy City Oral History Project 4/20/05, 2005-04-20 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Entire CD is Clifford Coulson interview. CD-R, 700 MB, 80 min. Memorex. In purple plastic sleeve.
  - Jackie Council and Elaine Smith 26:53 - Empower DC's Ivy City Oral History Project, 2006-07-24 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Entire CD is Lula "Jackie" Council and Elaine Smith interview. CD-R, 700 MB, 80 min. Memorex. In plastic CD jewel case.
  - Erica Crews - 13:13 Empower DC's Oral History Project (Ivy City), undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Entire CD is Erica Crews interview. CD-R, 700 MB, 80 min. Memorex. In green plastic sleeve.
  - Remetter Freeman - Disc 1/2: 49:10 - Empower DC's Ivy City Oral History Project 6/14/06, 2006-06-14 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Disc 1 of 2 discs of Remetter Freeman interview. CD-R, 700 MB, 80 min. Memorex. Both discss in blue plastic sleeve.
  - Remetter Freeman - Disc 2/2: 33:27 - Empower DC's Ivy City Oral History Project 6/14/06, 2006-06-14 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Disc 2 of 2 discs of Remetter Freeman interview. CD-R, 700 MB, 80 min. Memorex. Both discs in blue plastic sleeve.
  - Eleanor Grant and Daisy Wroten - Disc 1/2 - 43:45 - Empower DC's Ivy City Oral History Project 12/19/05, 2005-12-19 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Disc 1 of 2 discs of Eleanor Grant and Daisy Wroten interview. CD-R, 700 MB, 80 min. Memorex. Both discs in one blue plastic sleeve.
  - Eleanor Grant and Daisy Wroten - Disc 2/2 - 36:12 - Empower DC's Ivy City Oral History Project 12/19/05, 2005-12-19 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Disc 2 of 2 discs of Eleanor Grant and Daisy Wroten interview. CD-R, 700 MB, 80 min. Memorex. Both discs in one blue plastic sleeve.
  - Dorothy "Nicey" Gray Ivy City Oral History Project 3/7/05, 2005-03-07 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Entire CD is Dorothy "Nicey" Gray interview. CD-R Audio, 80 min. Sony. In purple plastic sleeve.
  - Marjorie Jones Ivy City Oral History Project 3/7/05, 2005-03-07 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Entire CD is Marjorie Jones interview. CD-R, 700 MB, 80 min. Memorex. In pink plastic sleeve.
  - Joel McPherson - 26:18 - Empower DC's Ivy City Oral History Project, 2006-07-16 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Entire CD is Joel McPherson interview. CD-R, 700 MB, 80 min. Memorex. In plastic CD jewel case.
  - Aujeneah Milner - 11:23 Okia Ferguson 11:13 - Empower DC's Ivy City Oral History Project, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Aujeneah Milner - 11:23, undated (Item 1)
      Track 1 of Disc 1 of Milner/Ferguson interview. CD-R, 700 MB, 80 min. Memorex. In plastic CD jewel case.
    - Okia Ferguson 11:13, undated (Item 2)
      Track 2 of Disc 1 of Milner/Ferguson interview. CD-R, 700 MB, 80 min. Memorex. In plastic CD jewel case.
  - Mohammed Mobaidin Ivy City Oral History Project, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Entire CD is Mohammed Mobaidin interview. CD-R, 700 MB, 80 min. Memorex. In green plastic sleeve.
  - Parisa Norouzi, 8/22/06 Ivy City Oral History Project, 2006-08-22 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Entire CD is Parisa Norouzi interview. CD-R, 700 MB, 80 min. Memorex. In purple plastic sleeve.
  - Audrey Ray - 58:56 - Empower DC's Ivy City Oral History Project, 2006-07-16 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Entire CD is Audrey Ray interview. CD-R, 700 MB, 80 min. Memorex. In plastic CD jewel case.
  - Margaret Rice and Sarah Parker Hunter - 63:02 - Empower DC's Oral History Project (Ivy City) 3/16/05, 2005-03-16 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Entire CD is Margaret Rice and Sarah Parker Hunter interview. CD-R, 700 MB, 80 min. Memorex. In purple plastic sleeve.
  - Kenneth Tapscott - 39:38 Empower DC's Oral History Project (Ivy City) 12/9/05, 2005-12-09 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Entire CD is Kenneth Tapscott interview. CD-R, 700 MB, 80 min. Memorex. In purple plastic sleeve.
  - Romaine Thomas 8/17/06 Ivy City Oral History Project, 2006-08-17 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Entire CD is Romaine Thomas interview. CD-R Audio, 80 min. In purple plastic sleeve.
  - Charlotte Tyner - 52:03 - Empower DC's Ivy City Oral History Project 8/29/05, 2005-08-29 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Entire CD is Charlotte Tyner interview. CD-R, 700 MB, 80 min. Memorex. In purple plastic sleeve.
  - Ivy City Oral History Project - Transcripts, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    CD-R, 700 MB, 80 min. Memorex. In plastic CD jewel case. Post-It note on front of case reads: The transcriptions of Ivy City interviews can be printed out from these files on disc.
- Series 2: Photographs
  - Photos of Ivy City Interviewees, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Photo of Aaron Aylor. Ivy City Oral History Project., 2006-07-15 (Item 1)
      Color 4"x6" photo of Aaron Aylor, labeled in ink on the back; he's seated on the front steps of a building.
    - Photo of Charles Brown. Ivy City Oral History Project., 2006-08-02 (Item 2)
      Color 4"x6" photo of Charles Brown, labeled in ink on back; he's standing on front steps of a building, cigarette in his mouth, holding a miniature slugger baseball bat over his shoulder.
    - Photo of Alfred Coates and Theodore Coates. Ivy City Oral History Project., 2005-06-20 (Item 3)
      Color 4"x6" photo of Alfred Coates (right) and Theodore Coates (left), labeled on back in ink; both men are seated.
    - Photo of Clifford Coulson. Ivy City Oral History Project., 2005-04-20 (Item 4)
      Color 4"x6" photo of Clifford Coulson, labeled on the back in ink; he's holding old photographs.
    - Photo of Jackie Council and Elaine Smith. Ivy City Oral History Project., 2006-07-24 (Item 5)
      Color 4"x6" photo of Jackie Council and Elaine Smith, labeled in ink on the back; no indication of who is who. Both are seated.
    - Photo of Remetter Freeman. Ivy City Oral History Project., 2006-06-14 (Item 6)
      Color 4"x6" photo of Remetter Freeman, labeled in ink on the back; she's standing in a front yard amongst flowers in a garden.
    - Photo of Mohammed Mobaidin. Ivy City Oral History Project., undated (Item 7)
      Color 4"x6" photo of Mohammed Mobaidan, labeled on the back in ink; he's standing outside in front of a gray brick wall.
    - Photo of Parisa Norouzi. Ivy City Oral History Project., undated (Item 8)
      Color 4"x6" printout of digital photo of Paris Norouzi on HP photo paper, printed white label on front; she's seated in chair with floral headwrap on. Unidentified woman is in the foreground.
    - Photo of Audrey Ray. Ivy City Oral History Project., undated (Item 9)
      Color 4"x6" printout of digital photo of Audrey Ray on HP photo paper ,printed type on white label on front; she's standing in a yard, gesturing toward a large growth of ivy.
    - Photo of Romaine Thomas. Ivy City Oral History Project., 2006-08-17 (Item 10)
      Color 4"x6" photo of Romaine Thomas, labeled in ink on the back; she's standing in front of the porch of a house.
    - Photo of Charlotte Tyner. Ivy City Oral History Project., 2005-08-29 (Item 11)
      Color 4"x6" photo of Charlotte Tyner, labeled on the back in ink; she's seated in a chair with two stuffed animals.